













    
        
    

    
        
    







    

    






<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"  xml:lang="en-us"  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <channel>
        
            

            
                
            

            
                <link href="//localhost:1313/tags/resource-management/" rel="self" type="text/html"/>
            
        
            

            

            
                <link href="//localhost:1313/tags/resource-management/index.xml" rel="alternate" type="application/rss+xml"/>
            
        

        

        

        <description></description>

        
            <language>en-us</language>
        

        
            <lastBuildDate>2024-10-04 16:58:35 &#43;0200 CEST</lastBuildDate>
        

        <link>//localhost:1313/tags/resource-management/</link>

        

        <title>Resource Management · Tags · </title>

        

        
            <item>
                
                
                
                
                
                
                

                

                

                

                

                
                

                

                

                
                    <description><![CDATA[<style>

:target:before {
  content: ''
  display: block;
  height: 100px; /* Adjust offset as needed */
  margin-top: -100px; /* Negative value equal to height */
  visibility: hidden;
}

html {
  scroll-behavior: smooth; /* Enable smooth scrolling behavior */
}

</style>
<p>Resource management in game engines is a wide term, from handling newly exported assets to managing assets loaded into memory in a specific form for particular engine modules. In this article I describe the most basic form of resource management – based on reference counting and sharing one resource allocated in memory. <strong>Why is this so important?</strong></p>
<h1 id="nie-pushuj-nic-na-repo-bez-ustawiania-tego-na-draft-">NIE PUSHUJ NIC NA REPO BEZ USTAWIANIA TEGO NA DRAFT 🚩🚩🚩🚩🚩🚩🚩🚩🚩🚩🚩🚩🚩🚩🚩🚩🚩🚩</h1>
<h2 id="background">Background</h2>
<p>I present this topic in context of a simple game engine I coworked on. My team and I developed a simple game engine, and a game made with it, in <strong>4 months</strong> for courses conducted by the <a href="https://p.lodz.pl/en">Lodz University of Technology</a>.</p>
<p>You can check the project <a href="/portfolio/guiding-light/">right there</a> – more technical aspects of the engine are presented under this link, but I will also delve into some details in this post, where needed. But now, let&rsquo;s answer the question from the introduction: <strong>Why is resource management so important, even in simple custom game engines and educational projects?</strong></p>
<p>By writing this post I want to guide mostly rookie engine devs, based on my contribution to our student project. That results in a few significant aspects you need to know, before you dive into the post&hellip;</p>
<h2 id="what-you-need-to-be-aware-of">What You Need to Be Aware of</h2>
<h2 id="summary">Summary</h2>
<h2 id="sources--additional-materials">Sources &amp; Additional Materials</h2>
]]></description>
                

                <guid isPermaLink="false">tag:localhost:1313,2024-10-04:/blog/post-3/</guid>

                
                    <link>//localhost:1313/blog/post-3/</link>
                

                
                    <pubDate>Fri, 04 Oct 2024 16:58:35 CEST</pubDate>
                

                
                    <title>Basic Resource Management in a Custom Game Engine</title>
                
            </item>
        
    </channel>
</rss>
